<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 1998-2010 by xTuple. All rights reserved. -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>System Administration</title>
  <para>Before you can begin processing retail sales, you must first set up
  xTuple POS to reflect your retail operation&mdash;and give users the
  required permissions to use the retail package. These activities should be
  completed by a retail operations manager or dedicated information technology
  professional. In this chapter we'll cover the following topics:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Configuring User Permissions</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Configuring the Sales module</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Creating Retail Sites</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>Once these configurations are complete, you can begin selling
  products!</para>
  <section>
    <title>Configuring User Permissions</title>
    <para>xTuple ERP has the powerful ability to manage user permissions,
    enabling you to allow or disallow access to various functional areas of
    the system. For example, a sales associate may only have privileges to
    process sales, while the store manager may have the ability to maintain
    registers, view inventory, and process sales.</para>
    <para>There are several options available to you when managing system
    users. You can either A) assign individual permissions to users B) create
    preconfigured groups of permissions and assign individuals to these groups
    or C) a combination of A and B.</para>
    <para>The following path will get you to the screen for maintaining system
    users: <guimenuitem>System &gt; Maintain Users</guimenuitem>.</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/xtpospermissions.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>List Users</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>In this scenario, let's say we have a new sales associate whose
    permissions we want to review. To begin, follow these steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Highlight the user whose permissions we want to review</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the EDIT button (or double-click on the user)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The following screen will appear:</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/xtpospermissions2.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>User Privileges</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>As you can see, the basic user information&mdash;such as name and
    email address&mdash;has already been entered. The user also has several
    Sales module privileges, which you can see under the "Granted Privileges"
    section. We can add or remove privileges (by module) simply by selecting a
    specific privilege, and then choosing either the ADD or REVOKE
    button.</para>
    <tip>
      <para>Use the ADD ALL and REVOKE ALL buttons to move all the privileges
      at once for the specified module</para>
    </tip>
    <para>To learn which groups our sample user belongs to, we select the
    "Groups" tab. The following screen appears:</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/xtpospermissions3.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>User Groups</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>In this case, the following user groups have been defined:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>ADMIN</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>OPS MANAGER</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>STORE MANAGER</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>SALES ASSOCIATE</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>As you can see, our user has been granted the privileges for the
    SALES ASSOCIATE group. If we wanted to change the group the user belonged
    to, we could simply use the ADD or REVOKE buttons. We could also add
    individual privileges to the user's existing group privileges by using the
    same buttons on the "Privileges" tab.</para>
    <tip>
      <para>The user group feature makes it easy to define logical sets of
      privileges defined according to standard job roles. The following path
      takes you to the screen for defining group privileges:
      <guimenuitem>System &gt; Maintain Groups</guimenuitem>.</para>
    </tip>
    <para>To review the Sites our sample user has access to, select the
    "Sites" tab. The following screen will appear:</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/xtpospermissions4.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>User Information Sites</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>Since our user is a sales associate at the ST1 Site, he only has
    permission to access this one Site. If, on the other hand, he were an
    operations manager, he might have permissions to access every Site. This
    would enable him to review inventory levels or sales reports across the
    entire operation.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Configuring the Sales Module</title>
    <para>The first step in configuring xTuple POS is to enter some basic
    global information. To do this, navigate to the Sales Configuration screen
    in the System module, using the following steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Follow this path: <guimenuitem>System &gt; Configure Modules
        &gt; Sales</guimenuitem></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the "Retail" tab</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The following screen will appear:</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/configureSO_configureRetail.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Retail Configuration Options</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>All retail transactions automatically receive a unique ID number. On
    the Sales Configuration screen you define which number you want to use as
    the starting point for these unique identifiers. You can choose any
    initial number you wish.</para>
    <tip>
      <para>To ensure you are collecting customer information at the point of
      sale, be sure <emphasis>not</emphasis> to select the "Use internal
      customer for all Retail Sales" option.</para>
    </tip>
    <para>In addition, you have the option on this screen to decide if you
    want to collect customer data at the point of sale&mdash;such as customer
    name, address, and phone number&mdash;or not. If you prefer not to collect
    this information, then select the "Disable choosing Customer at Cash
    Register" option. This will cause the customer tab on the Cash Register
    screen to be hidden from view. To learn more about the system-wide options
    for configuring the Retail package, please see the xTuple Reference
    Guide.</para>
    <para>Finally, you will need to determine whether the Tax Zone for your
    Retail sales is drawn from the Site record or from the Customer record. If
    you are not collecting Customer information at the point of sale, then the
    Site option would be your choice.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Creating Retail Sites</title>
    <para>In xTuple ERP, we define "Sites" as physical locations where you
    operate your business. For example, in the PostBooks Edition&mdash;our
    free ERP offering&mdash;we provide you with the ability to manage a single
    Site. A Site can be a store front, warehouse, or corporate office. One of
    the benefits of the commercial editions of xTuple ERP is that you gain the
    ability to manage multiple Sites, including any combination of Site types.
    Depending on your level of permissions, the multi-Site capability gives
    you the ability to track sales remotely at multiple stores and also
    monitor inventory levels at each Site.</para>
    <note>
      <para>The examples used in this product guide are based on having xTuple
      POS loaded into the Manufacturing Edition of xTuple ERP.</para>
    </note>
    <para>Sites are added (or edited) in the Inventory module. The following
    path will get you there: <guimenuitem>Inventory &gt; Site &gt;
    List</guimenuitem>. The following screen shows a list of the two store
    front operations we will be using throughout this product guide: ST1 and
    ST2. We will later assign Cash Register terminals to these Sites.</para>
    <note>
      <para>Keep in mind, Sites are not necessarily limited to store fronts
      only. Warehouses, factories, and business offices may also be identified
      as Sites.</para>
    </note>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/listsites.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>List Sites</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <tip>
      <para>Make sure when creating a new Site that you enter a Tax Authority
      on the General tab for each Site that will have a store front. Sales
      taxes will be calculated by the Cash Register windows based on the Tax
      Authority defined at the Site level.</para>
    </tip>
    <para>Once you enter your list of Sites, the next step is to define Retail
    Sites. The difference between "Sites" and "Retail Sites" is that Retails
    Sites hold additional information specific to the xTuple POS package. For
    example, default cost accounts and Cash Register terminals are defined at
    the Retail Site level. The following path will get you to the Retail Sites
    screen: <guimenuitem>Sales &gt; Master Information &gt; Retail
    Sites</guimenuitem>.</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/retailsitesST1.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>List of Retail Sites</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>As you can see in our example, we have already created the Retail
    Site for the ST1 Site. We will now demonstrate how this was done by
    creating a Retail Site for the ST2 Site. To begin creating a new Retail
    Site, select the NEW button. The following screen will appear:</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/retailsiteST2a.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Create Retail Site</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>On this screen complete the following steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Choose the Site you want to define as a Retail Site</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Specify how long you want Quotes to remain active for this
        Retail Site</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Assign default cost accounts assigned to the Retail Site</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Indicate the Bank Account(s) used by this Retail Site for
        depositing and transferring funds</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>The next step is to define Terminals to associate with the Retail
    Site. Terminals are required when using a Cash Register, as will be
    discussed in later chapters. To define a Terminal, select the "Terminals"
    tab and complete the following steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the ADD button</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Type in the name of the Terminal in the line provided (e.g.,
        Terminal 2a)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Again select the ADD button if more Terminals are needed</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/retailsiteST2b.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Add Cash Register Terminals</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>Now that our Retail Sites have been created, we can begin managing
    the Cash Registers and processing sales!</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
