<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 1998-2010 by xTuple. All rights reserved. -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>Installation</title>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>xTuple POS&mdash;otherwise known as
    <literal>xtpos</literal>&mdash;is an xTuple extension package which may be
    applied to any xTuple ERP edition. The package is easy to install. And
    once installed, it seamlessly integrates point of sale functionality with
    your ERP.</para>
    <para>To install xTuple POS, you will need the following items:</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Updater tool</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This is the package installer. It is a cross-platform
          application which connects to your xTuple ERP database and installs
          the xTuple POS package (<literal>xtpos</literal>). The Updater is
          the same tool that is used for upgrading xTuple ERP databases from
          one version to the next. It also converts xTuple ERP from one
          edition to the next (e.g., PostBooks to Standard).</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>xTuple POS package (xtpos)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This is the xTuple extension package which integrates point of
          sale features with your xTuple ERP. The file is loaded into the
          Updater, which in turn applies the package to your xTuple database.
          And like all xTuple database upgrade scripts, the file ends with a
          <filename><literal>.gz</literal></filename> extension.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Getting the Required Files</title>
    <para>If you purchased xTuple POS on the xTuple xChange, then you should
    already have the files you need&mdash;that is, the Updater tool and the
    <literal>xtpos</literal> package. We will explain how to install the
    package in the next section.</para>
    <note>
      <para>Depending on which edition of xTuple ERP you are running, it may
      be possible to download the required files from the "Commercial
      Software" section of the <ulink url="www.xtuple.org">xtuple.org</ulink>
      website.</para>
    </note>
    <para>The Updater tool can also be downloaded from the PostBooks project
    page on SourceForge.net. To reach the PostBooks project, follow these
    steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Point your web browser to <ulink
        url="http://sourceforge.net/">http://sourceforge.net/</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Search for the PostBooks project</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Or use the direct URL: <ulink
        url="???">http://sourceforge.net/projects/postbooks/</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The following project page will appear. The details may vary
        slightly, depending on the version you are downloading:</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/sourceforge.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>PostBooks Project Home Page</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>Next, select the "View All Files" button. Once you select this
    button, you will see the full list of all files available for download.
    The following screenshot shows several of the file folders used to
    organize the file downloads. Simply click on one of the folders to reveal
    the available files inside the folder.</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/sourceforge2.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>PostBooks Packages Download Page</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <tip>
      <para>If at first you don't see the Updater folder on the Downloads
      page, make sure to scroll all the way down the web page until you find
      it.</para>
    </tip>
    <para>Finally, select the Updater folder and click on it to reveal the
    files contained in the folder. Be sure to choose the file which
    corresponds to your operating system. The Updater is available for
    Windows, Mac, and Linux, as shown in the following screen:</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/sourceforge3.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Download Updater</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>Once you've downloaded the Updater and the <literal>xtpos</literal>
    package, you are ready to begin the installation!</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Installing the Package</title>
    <para>Having xTuple ERP installed and running is a prerequisite for
    installing xTuple POS. Assuming this is the case, then you are ready to
    begin.</para>
    <note>
      <para>Before you install the xTuple POS package, you should first make a
      backup copy of your xTuple ERP database. This way you can always restore
      the backup copy should you encounter problems during the installation
      process.</para>
    </note>
    <para>To begin installing the xTuple POS package, the first step is to
    connect the Updater to your xTuple ERP database. The process for
    connecting is identical to the process used when logging in using your
    xTuple ERP client software.</para>
    <para>The following screen shows the log in screen you are presented with
    when launch the Updater application:</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/updaterLogin.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Connect to xTuple Database Using Updater</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <tip>
      <para>If you are having trouble connecting to your xTuple ERP database
      with the Updater, select the OPTIONS button on the Log In screen to
      ensure your connection information is correct.</para>
    </tip>
    <para>Once you successfully connect to the database, you are ready to load
    the <literal>xtpos</literal> package. To begin loading the
    <literal>xtpos</literal> package, follow these steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the "File" menu option</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the "Open" option, as shown in the following
        screen:</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/loadUpdater.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Load Package into Updater</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>Once you locate the <literal>xtpos</literal> package on your file
    system (e.g., <filename><filename>xtpos-3.5.0.gz</filename></filename>), a
    short series of prerequisite checks will be performed. The following
    screen shows the results of a successful prerequisite check:</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/updatemanage.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Update Manager and Package</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>If the prerequisite check was successful, simply select the START
    UPDATE button to complete installation. Depending on the quality of your
    network connection, this final step of the installation process should
    complete quickly.</para>
    <note>
      <para>Contact your system administrator if you encounter errors or
      extreme slowness after selecting the START UPDATE button.</para>
    </note>
    <para>To verify the xTuple POS package has been successfully installed,
    log into xTuple ERP. Finally, navigate to the installed packages
    directory, using the following path: <guimenuitem>System &gt; Design &gt;
    Packages</guimenuitem>. If xTuple POS was installed correctly, the package
    should appear as shown in the following screen:</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/listpackages.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Package Installed in xTuple ERP</caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </section>
</chapter>
