<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 1998-2010 by xTuple. All rights reserved. -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<preface>
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <section>
    <title>Product Overview</title>
    <para>xTuple POS adds retail functionality on top of the foundation of
    xTuple ERP. This means that in addition to the xTuple POS retail features,
    you also have access to the full range of advanced ERP features&mdash;such
    as accounting, inventory management, and customer relationship management
    (CRM). xTuple POS is designed to allow you to track and process sales
    using a cash register system, providing your operation with historical and
    real time data from retail sales. However, the system is not limited to
    sales data. You can also collect data regarding inventory availability,
    returns, quotes, customer information, commissions and more. Having all
    this data available at your finger tips improves your ability to serve
    your customers!</para>
    <para>Here are just a few real world examples of how xTuple POS can help
    you:</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Visibility Across Multiple Stores</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If you need to track down an item for a customer because it's
          out of stock in Store A, you can use xTuple POS to learn if the same
          item is available at Store B.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Detailed Sales History</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>When customers have questions about recent purchases, you can
          quickly access sale and item information to provide excellent
          customer service. Using either a receipt number or basic customer
          information&mdash;such as phone number&mdash;you can answer any
          number of questions regarding date of sale, purchase price,
          discounts, item description, etc.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Inventory Control</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Because you can track inventory and shopping patterns, the
          retailer's buying process is made much more effective. Visibility
          into slow moving inventory enables you to provide your customers
          with the products they want in a timely fashion&mdash;instead of
          spending endless hours speculating over what consumers may or may
          not purchase.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>This xTuple POS Product Guide will walk you through the process of
    installing, configuring, and using xTuple POS system for your retail
    operation.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Choosing an xTuple ERP Edition</title>
    <para>xTuple POS is available for use by all xTuple ERP editions. This
    means you will have full-scale ERP functionality underlying your xTuple
    POS installation.</para>
    <para>If you are uncertain which xTuple ERP edition is the right one for
    you, our sales staff would be happy to help you make your decision. To
    contact us, simply send an email requesting more information to <ulink
    url="mailto:sales@xtuple.com">sales@xtuple.com</ulink>.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Open Source Software: What is it and what does it mean to
    me?</title>
    <para>By now you may have heard some buzz about open source
    software&mdash;and you're not sure what to make of it. It may even sound
    like a bunch of technical jargon used to impress IT professionals, which
    may or may not apply to yourself. This is all the more reason why we want
    to provide you with a little insight into what open source software is and
    what it means to you.</para>
    <para>In a nutshell, open source software provides users with access to
    software source code. By source code, we mean the programming files that
    form the basis for a software product. Open source software is different
    from closed source software, in that closed source software locks up its
    source code and hides it from end users. Traditionally, closed source
    software has been the more common form of commercial "boxed" software
    products that you would pick up at your local office store. A result of
    the open source movement has been several licensing and distribution
    models:</para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Community license</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Applications are free to anyone and developed as projects in
          large groups based on public input.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Dual license</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A combination of free and commercial applications. A company
          may provide some software tools that are free to the public, while
          others are sold commercially.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Shared source license</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Commercial software where the source code may be viewed;
          however, there is no ability to make changes to the code.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <note>
      <para>xTuple software generally falls under the second category: "dual
      license." That's because we offer both free and commercial applications,
      with our source code available for review and change.</para>
    </note>
    <para>Still wondering what all this means to you? Well, what it means is
    that the software we've created has grown based on direct feedback from
    YOU our user community.</para>
    <para>At xTuple, we don't hide our work from public scrutiny. Rather, we
    present our work for all to see. We do this to promote shared insight into
    how we can continue to improve the software to make your job easier. In
    fact, on the xTuple community website we encourage you to provide direct
    feedback regarding bugs you've found or features you may find useful in
    the future. We also invite you to share your success stories and tips and
    tricks. In this way, you can reach out and help other xTuple community
    members.</para>
    <para>And, If you are an IT professional and a bit of a code jockey, you
    can even make changes to the source code on your local copy. Many of our
    greatest enhancements have been sponsored by our customers&mdash;and these
    changes have been rolled into the final product so that other users can
    benefit from the improvements. This means our tools and products are not
    designed solely by xTuple engineers. They are also designed by the people
    who use them everyday. We at xTuple encourage you to learn more about the
    community and get involved on the <ulink
    url="www.xtuple.org">xTuple.org</ulink> website. Rather than quietly
    grumbling to yourself about things you think could be better, reach out to
    fellow community members to find out how to make these changes
    happen!</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>xTuple Application Architecture</title>
    <para>The xTuple applications are designed on a two-tier system:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Graphical client built using the open source Qt development
        framework</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Database server running on the open source PostgreSQL
        database</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>All of the xTuple business logic resides in the database, so there
    is no middle tier (i.e., Java/application server). And the client is
    "thin". Since Qt and the PostgreSQL database are cross-platform solutions,
    the application can be installed on Mac, Windows, or Linux
    machines&mdash;in any combination you prefer. There is also a wireless
    client which runs on a hand-held bar code scanner.</para>
    <para>Installation of xTuple is easy and painless. Once you download the
    software, you then run the xTuple graphical client out of the directory it
    resides in. The same xTuple client can connect to a database for any of
    the xTuple ERP editions. Upgrading from one edition to the next involves
    little more than running a two-minute script on your database. The
    simplicity of the upgrade process illustrates the point that xTuple
    maintains a single code base for all of its ERP editions. Doing so enables
    our community of open source users to share and work together in one
    online hub for all the xTuple products.</para>
    <para>There are several layers of security available with xTuple ERP. You
    can utilize a Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) connection, and you can also
    enable an enhanced authentication mechanism which scrambles your users'
    passwords. In addition, you can also assign individual privileges with the
    system in as much detail as you see fit for your operation.</para>
  </section>
</preface>
