<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 1998-2010 by xTuple. All rights reserved. -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>Cash Register Maintenance</title>
  <para>As the manager of a retail store you are responsible for managing the
  Cash Register terminals. This responsibility includes the following
  duties:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Opening and closing registers each business day</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Adjusting funds in and out of registers during operation</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Monitoring transaction history throughout the day</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Reconciling registers at the end of business day</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>This chapter covers all these topics in detail and highlights tools
  and functionality that will make your job easier.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Opening the Cash Register Terminal</title>
    <para>The first task at hand each day after turning on the lights and
    before unlocking the doors of your store is to open your Cash Register
    terminals for business. For the scenarios described in this chapter, we
    will assume we have all privileges on all Cash Registers&mdash;and that we
    are running a multi-Site retail operation. The following path will get you
    to the list of Cash Register terminals: <guimenuitem>Sales &gt; Retail
    &gt; Cash Registers</guimenuitem>.</para>
    <para>As the following screenshot illustrates, our sample retail operation
    consists of five registers (TERMINALS 1A-2B) spread across two different
    Sites (ST1 and ST2):</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/cashregistersST1.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Cash Register Terminals</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>For this exercise, we will assume we are managing Store Front 1
    (ST1). We expect it will be a slow shopping day. And at this point all we
    want to do is open the TERMINAL 1A Cash Register. As you can see, all the
    Cash Registers are currently closed&mdash;and all have a $0
    balance.</para>
    <para>To open TERMINAL 1A, follow these steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Highlight TERMINAL 1A</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the USE button</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <tip>
      <para>You can also double-click a register to open it.</para>
    </tip>
    <para>Once you open the register, you are presented with the following
    screen:</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/cashregisteropen2.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Cash Register Terminal</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>The main register screen provides information about pending Sales
    for the register&mdash;as well as links to other features will we will
    explore in other sections.</para>
    <para>Meanwhile, let's continue our focus on basic Cash Register
    maintenance. To reach the maintenance area, select the "Maintain" tab. The
    following screen will appear:</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/cashregisteropen.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Maintain Terminal</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>Our task this morning is to open TERMINAL 1A with a balance of
    $250&mdash;and that's exactly what we are going to do. As you can see in
    the screenshot, the maintenance screen allows for bank transfers and also
    adjustments. For now, we will focus on bank transfers, because we want to
    get the register open and ready for business. Later, we will discuss how
    to handle miscellaneous adjustments.</para>
    <para>To open the register, follow these steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>From the "Action" field, select the "Open" option</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Under the "Bank Transfer" section, choose the Bank Account you
        want to transfer money from</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Enter the amount of money you want to transfer into the terminal
        (i.e., $250 in our example)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Specify "In" next to the "Amount" field to indicate money is
        going <emphasis>into</emphasis> the terminal</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Note the New Balance amount&mdash;and make sure it is
        correct</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Make sure the "Print Receipt" option is selected. (The default
        print settings can be changed using the OPTIONS button. These settings
        are particular to this screen&mdash;and to the terminal you are
        working on.)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Finally, select the POST button</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Your register is now ready to begin processing Sales!</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <tip>
      <para>If cash for opening balances is maintained on the store premises
      in a safe, you can create an asset account and a Bank Account for your
      safe. This will help you closely track all funds transferred between
      register, safe, and bank.</para>
    </tip>
    <para>Returning to the Cash Register list, we now see that TERMINAL 1A is
    ready for business:</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/cashregistersopen.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Open Cash Registers List</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>Not only is TERMINAL 1A showing as active, but it also has a time
    stamp indicating when the register was opened. The current opening balance
    for the register is also indicated.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Adjusting the Cash Register Terminal</title>
    <para>It's not uncommon for a Cash Register to be thrown out of balance
    during the course of the business day. Sometimes the balance due is
    counted out wrong, and sometimes you'll have a customer who wants the
    store to keep the change. In these instances&mdash;when overages or losses
    are encountered&mdash;it's important to have a mechanism enabling managers
    to make minor adjustments. Once again, user permissions define who in the
    store has the ability to adjust the register balance.</para>
    <para>If a Cash Register adjustment is required, use the "Adjustment"
    section of the maintenance window, as shown in the following
    screen:</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/cashregisteradj.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Adjust Cash Register Terminal</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>The adjustment process is similar to opening a register. For this
    example, let's say the Cash Register is over by $0.85&mdash;due to a
    transaction error. To adjust for an overage, follow these steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>From the "Action" field, select the "Adjust" option</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Enter $0.85 as the amount to be transferred in or out of the
        register</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Specify "Out" next to the "Amount" field to indicate money is
        going <emphasis>out of</emphasis> the terminal</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Finally, select the POST button</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Notice the current balance updates after adjustment is
        posted</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <note>
      <para>Be careful not to confuse the adjustment transaction with the bank
      transfer transaction. Adjustments should be used for money that is not
      accounted for by any other type of transaction. For example, if your
      cash drawer becomes full on a particularly busy shopping day and you
      need to transfer money out of the drawer and into a safe, use the bank
      transfer transaction.</para>
    </note>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Closing the Cash Register</title>
    <para>Once the business day is over, you are ready to close and reconcile
    the Cash Register. Closing the Cash Register also updates the General
    Ledger (G/L) with all the sales and cash transaction information generated
    during the course of the day. This final accounting for sales and cash
    information only hits the G/L when the Cash Register is closed. By
    contrast, inventory movement is tracked in the G/L on a sale-by-sale
    basis.</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/cashregisterclose.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Close Cash Register Terminal</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>For this example, we will be transferring all the cash out of the
    TERMINAL 1A Cash Register&mdash;and depositing it into our Bank Account.
    We will also plan to deposit any Checks we have received during the day.
    To do this, follow these steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>From the "Action" field, select the "Close" option</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Under the "Bank Transfer" section, choose the Bank Account you
        want to transfer money to</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Enter the amount of cash you want to transfer to the Bank
        Account</para>
        <note>
          <para>Keep in mind that the current balance in the register includes
          only cash. Checks are not included in the current balance
          amount.</para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>By default, the "Deposit Checks" option should be automatically
        selected</para>
        <note>
          <para>The "Deposit Checks" option ensures that the total amount of
          Check Sales for the register will be recorded in the General
          Ledger.</para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Verify the "Print Receipt" option is selected in the lower
        left-hand corner of the screen</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the POST button</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>View the Cash Register receipt</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/closereport.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Cash Register Receipt</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>If the sum of the physical cash and Checks from the register equal
    the totals on the Register Posting Receipt, you're ready to make your bank
    deposit.</para>
    <para>In the event that your Cash Register terminal does not balance you
    can review the Detailed Register History screen to research transaction
    errors. Use the following path to reach the detailed history screen:
    <guimenuitem>Sales &gt; Reports &gt; Detailed Register
    History</guimenuitem>.</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/dspDetailedRegisterHistory.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Detailed Register History</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>You will notice from the screen shot above this screen provides
    detailed information such as transaction type, user, tender, and items
    purchased. This screen also gives you the ability to search by a specific
    terminal on a specific date. While in our example the Cash Register
    actually balanced we may need to research other information. For example,
    perhaps customer 102 is a notorious check bouncer and we would like to
    find out how many purchases they made today. We can see from the report
    that this customer made two purchases on TERMINAL 1A and wrote two checks
    3455 and 1990. The store manager could then flag these checks to verify
    funds.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Cash Register Maintenance History</title>
    <para>You can review register history at any time to determine when a
    terminal was opened, closed, and adjusted. Use the following path to reach
    the register history screen: <guimenuitem>Sales &gt; Reports &gt; Register
    History</guimenuitem>.</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/registerhistory.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Cash Register Maintenance History</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>In this screen shot we can see on the first line that TERMINAL 1A
    was opened on 3/12/09 and $250 was transferred in the Cash Register. This
    screen could be very useful in a multi-site operation where a manager may
    want to find out how many registers are open at each store or if a manager
    reports to work mid-day and needs to know which terminals are open at the
    store.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
