<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 1998-2010 by xTuple. All rights reserved. -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>Generating Quotes</title>
  <para>Sometimes you will have Customers who come to your store looking for
  an Item, but for whatever reason they are unable to purchase it at that
  time. They may be shopping around comparing prices—or your store might be
  out of stock. Whatever the reason may be, you can still capture the
  potential Sale and provide the Customer with a price Quote. This Quote can
  then be converted to a Sale at a later date. The following topics will be
  discussed in this chapter:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Creating Quotes</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Searching for Quotes</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Converting Quotes to Sales</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Deleting Quotes</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <section>
    <title>Creating Quotes</title>
    <para>Creating Quotes is very similar to creating Sales. They both use the
    Retail Sale screen. However, the difference is they use different Sale
    Types. To create a Quote, follow these steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Open the Retail Sale screen using the NEW button on the Cash
        Register screen</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In the "Number" field, the next available number is entered
        automatically</para>
        <note>
          <para>Sales, Quotes, and Returns all share the same numbering
          system. The number is a unique identifier used to identify the
          particular transaction.</para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>From the "Type" field, select the "Quote" option</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the NEW button to enter Customer information—or, for
        repeat Customers, use the Customer lookup button [...]</para>
        <note>
          <para>Capturing Customer information can be useful for marketing
          (and other) purposes. However, you can configure xTuple POS to not
          require Customer information at the point of sale. If no Customer
          information is required, then the "Customer" tab on the Retail Sale
          screen will be hidden.</para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The following screen shows a sample Quote in progress:</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/retailsalequote.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Retail Sale Quote</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>Quote Items are entered in the same way as Sale Items. To begin
    entering Quote Items, follow these steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the "Items" tab</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the ADD button</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Specify a Quote Item in the "Item Number" field</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Then enter the quantity being quoted</para>
        <note>
          <para>Item Pricing is configured using xTuple ERP. For more
          information on Item Pricing, please consult the xTuple ERP Reference
          Guide.</para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The following screen shows a sample Quote in progress:</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/retailsalequoteitems.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Retail Sale Quote Items</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <tip>
      <para>You can add Quote Items to a Quote using the following
      methods:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Scanning Item bar codes</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Typing Item Numbers in manually,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Locating products using the Item lookup button [...]</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </tip>
    <para>To enter Quote details, select the "Details" tab. This tab includes
    additional information you may need to collect regarding the
    Quote—including the name of the sales associate who processed the Quote
    and any miscellaneous notes you may want to record.</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/retailsalequotedetail.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Retail Sale Quote Detail</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <note>
      <para>A Sales Rep is required to successfully complete a Quote. If you
      cannot complete a Quote (e.g., cannot select the SAVE button), this may
      mean you have not specified a Sales Rep on the Quote "Detail"
      screen.</para>
    </note>
    <para>The system can be configured to automatically make the logged-in
    user the Sales Rep for a Quote. This configuration is discussed in more
    detail in the xTuple ERP Reference Guide. However, the following points
    provide an overview of the process:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Locate Employee records following this path: <guimenuitem>System
        &gt; Employees</guimenuitem></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Create Employee records for your system users</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>On Employee records, specify Employees are Sales Reps</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Create Sales Rep records for Employees</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Now when users log in, they will be recognized as a Sales
        Reps</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>To complete the Quote and save it for future reference, select the
    SAVE button. Saving a Quote brings us to the "Sales" tab of the Cash
    Register screen, as shown below:</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/cashregisterquote.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Quote Added to Cash Register</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>To print a copy of the Quote for the Customer to take with them,
    simply follow these steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Highlight the Quote record you want to print</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the PRINT button</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A sample Quote receipt is shown below:</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/retailsalequotereceipt.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Retail Sale Quote Receipt</caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Searching for Quotes</title>
    <para>If a Customer returns at a later date to purchase an Item based on a
    Quote you provided earlier, sales associates should have no trouble
    locating that information using xTuple POS. Follow these steps to search
    for Quotes:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Start on the Cash Register screen</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the SEARCH button to open the Retail Sale Search
        screen</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>From the "Show" section, select the "Quotes" option</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Specify a date range to include the Quote's created date</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Optionally, enter keywords to limit the search. For example, if
        you know the Quote number was 100010, you could enter "100010" in the
        "Search" field.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the QUERY button to run the search</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>View the results, as shown in the following screen:</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/retailsalesearchquote.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Retail Sale Search</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <note>
      <para>You can also perform Sales searches from the main Retail menu.
      However, any results from searches performed from the main menu are
      view-only. To convert Quotes to Sales, you must use the SEARCH button on
      the Cash Register screen.</para>
    </note>
    <para>Once you have found the Quote you want, simply highlight it and
    select the EDIT button—or double-click on the Quote to open it.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Converting Quotes to Sales</title>
    <para>The process of converting a Quote to a Sale couldn't be easier. Once
    you have found the Quote using the Retail Sale Search, simply open the
    Quote for editing, as shown in the following screen:</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/retailsalequote.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Convert Quote to Sale</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>There are two ways you can convert a Quote to a Sale:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Change the Sale Type from "Quote" to "Sale"</para>
        <para>OR</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the PAYMENT button, which automatically converts Quotes
        to Sales</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Deleting Quotes</title>
    <para>Many times Customers will change their minds about a purchase. If
    you ever need to delete a Quote prior to its expiration date, simply open
    the Cash Register screen and follow these steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Highlight the Quote you want to delete</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the DELETE button</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>See the following screen for details:</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/cashregisterquote.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Delete Quote</caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </section>
</chapter>
