<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 1998-2010 by xTuple. All rights reserved. -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>Point of Sale</title>
  <para>Now that you've installed and set up xTuple POS, you are ready to
  begin processing Sales. In this chapter we will review how to process Cash
  Register Sales. The following topics will be covered:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Customer Information</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Sale Items</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Sale Details</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Payment Processing</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <section>
    <title>Customer Information</title>
    <para>The processing of retail Sales is handled by the Cash Register. And
    so for this scenario, we'll need to open a Cash Register to begin. To open
    a Cash Register, follow these steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Follow this path: <guimenuitem>Sales &gt; Retail &gt; Cash
        Registers</guimenuitem></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Highlight the Cash Register you want to use</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the USE button</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The following screen will appear:</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/cashregisterpending.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Cash Register Sales</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <note>
      <para>Any pending Sales or transactions which are incomplete will appear
      on the Cash Register's "Sales" screen. In the event that a Customer
      decides to continue shopping, you can save the Sale, service the next
      Customer, and then reopen the transaction to complete the Sale when the
      previous Customer returns.</para>
    </note>
    <para>Now that our Cash Register is open, let's begin a new Sale and
    capture the Customer's information. For this example, we'll assume this is
    a new Customer. To get started, follow these steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the NEW button&mdash;this will open the Retail Sale
        screen</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In the "Number" field, the next retail Sale number is entered
        automatically</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>From the "Type" field, select the "Sale" option</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the NEW button to enter Customer information</para>
        <note>
          <para>Capturing Customer information can be useful for marketing
          (and other) purposes. However, you can configure xTuple POS to not
          require Customer information at the point of sale. If no Customer
          information is required, then the "Customer" tab on the Retail Sale
          screen will be hidden.</para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Enter a Customer Number</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Enter a Customer Name</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Enter Customer billing information</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the OK button</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Customer information is now completed, as shown in the following
        screen:</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/cashregistercustomer.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Retail Sale Customer Information</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>If you have a repeat Customer, it is not necessary to re-enter the
    Customer's information. In that scenario, you would follow these
    steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the Customer lookup button [...]</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The following screen will appear:</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/searchforcustomer.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Search for Existing Customer</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>After you locate the repeat Customer's record, simply select it to
    associate the Customer information with the new Sale. Using this feature
    for repeat Customers will save time. You won't have to re-enter Customers'
    information each time they visit your store.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Sale Items</title>
    <para>Once you've entered Customer information, you are now ready to begin
    entering Sale Items. To begin entering Sale Items, follow these
    steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the "Items" tab</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the ADD button</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Specify a Sale Item in the "Item Number" field</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Then enter the quantity being sold</para>
        <note>
          <para>Item Pricing is configured using xTuple ERP. For more
          information on Item Pricing, please consult the xTuple ERP Reference
          Guide.</para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the ADD button again</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Specify another Sale Item</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Then enter the quantity being sold</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The results are shown in the following screen:</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/retailsaleitem.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Adding Items to a Retail Sale</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <tip>
      <para>If you add a Sale Item in error, simply highlight the line item
      and select the REMOVE button. This will remove the Item from the Sale.
      You may need to add the replacement item first, if there are no other
      line items on the Sale.</para>
    </tip>
    <para>You have several methods available to you when it comes to entering
    Sale Items:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>You can scan Item bar codes</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>You can type Item Numbers in manually</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Or you can locate products using the Item lookup button
        [...]</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The following screen shows what you will see when using the Item
    lookup button:</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/solditems.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Item Look Up</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <note>
      <para>At the bottom of the Retail Sale screen you will notice your
      running total. This total will include Tax (if recorded)&mdash;and the
      set up for Tax is part of your xTuple ERP accounting configuration.
      Please consult the xTuple ERP Reference Guide for more information on
      Tax configuration.</para>
    </note>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Sale Details</title>
    <para>The final tab on the Retail Sale screen is the "Detail" tab. This
    tab includes additional information you may need to collect regarding the
    Sale&mdash;including the name of the sales associate who processed the
    Sale and any miscellaneous notes you may want to record.</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/retailsaledetail.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Retail Sale Detail</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <note>
      <para>A Sales Rep is required to successfully complete a Sale. If you
      cannot complete a Sale (e.g., cannot select the SAVE button), this may
      mean you have not specified a Sales Rep on the Sale "Detail"
      screen.</para>
    </note>
    <para>The system can be configured to automatically make the logged-in
    user the Sales Rep for a Sale. This configuration is discussed in more
    detail in the xTuple ERP Reference Guide. However, the following points
    provide an overview of the process:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Locate Employee records: System &gt; Employees</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Create Employee records for your system users</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>On Employee records, specify Employees are Sales Reps</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Create Sales Rep records for Employees</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Now when users log in, they will be recognized as a Sales
        Reps</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Payment Processing</title>
    <para>Now that the Sale is complete, we are ready to process payment. From
    an accounting perspective, any inventory movement will be tracked in the
    General Ledger (G/L) as soon as you process the payment. The final
    accounting&mdash;including sale and cash information&mdash;will not hit
    the G/L until the point when the Cash Register is closed.</para>
    <para>To process a payment, follow these steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the PAYMENT button</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The following screen will appear:</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/retailsalepayment.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Retail Sale Payment</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <tip>
      <para>If the PAYMENT button is grayed out this could mean you still have
      required fields which have not yet been completed. Once all required
      fields have been completed, the PAYMENT button will activate&mdash;and
      you can then accept payment.</para>
    </tip>
    <para>As you can see in our example, the Customer has chosen to write a
    Check for the bulk of the Sale. The remaining balance will be paid in
    cash. This illustrates the ability of xTuple POS to accept split payments.
    Had the Customer wanted to pay with a Credit Card instead of a Check, we
    would have selected the "Credit Card" option&mdash;and then entered the
    required information. Keep in mind that you can only enter Check or Credit
    Card payments if the amount entered in the Cash amount field is less than
    the total due.</para>
    <para>To ensure the Customer gets a receipt as proof of the Sale, follow
    these steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the "Print Receipt" option. (The default print settings
        can be changed using the OPTIONS button. These settings are particular
        to this screen&mdash;and to the terminal you are working on.)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the OK button</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A sample Sales receipt is shown below:</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/retailsalereceipt.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Retail Sale Receipt</caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </section>
</chapter>
