<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Copyright (c) 1998-2010 by xTuple. All rights reserved. -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>Customer Service Tools</title>
  <para>To provide the best possible customer service, your sales associates
  need to be able to answer all kinds of Customer questions. Fortunately,
  xTuple POS runs on a powerful database platform which stores transaction
  history and manages inventory. This means that answers to even the most
  complicated sales and inventory questions are all available at your
  fingertips!</para>
  <section>
    <title>Sales History</title>
    <para>It's common for Customers to have questions about their Sales
    history. Perhaps you quoted prices to them in the past&mdash;or maybe they
    want to be reminded of their recent purchases. In the best case scenario,
    Customers will have their original receipt. But often they will
    not.</para>
    <para>Either way, xTuple POS provides tools for looking up any type of
    Customer transaction. And, depending on your permission level and xTuple
    ERP edition, you may be able to uncover detailed information across
    multiple stores (i.e., Sites). Let's say, for example, you want to find
    all recent Sales activity for a particular Customer. To do so, follow
    these steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Open the search screen using the following path:
        <guimenuitem>Sales &gt; Retail &gt; Retail Sale
        Search</guimenuitem></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Under the "Show" section, select "Sales," "Quotes," and
        "Returns"</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Specify a date range</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In the "Search" field, enter the Customer's last name (e.g.,
        "Smith")</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The following screen shows the results we get:</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/retailsalesearchsmith.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Retail Sale Search</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <tip>
      <para>If you have a copy of an original Sales receipt, simply enter the
      receipt number in the "Search" field to quickly locate the Sales
      transaction.</para>
    </tip>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Item Availability</title>
    <para>Another common question Customers ask is whether you have a specific
    Item available in stock. With xTuple POS, you can quickly research an Item
    using the Inventory Availability by Item screen. To access the Inventory
    Availability screen, follow these steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Follow this path: <guimenuitem>Inventory &gt; Reports &gt;
        Inventory Availability &gt; by Item</guimenuitem></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In the "Item Number" field, enter the Item Number</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Specify the Site you are researching</para>
        <note>
          <para>If you are using one of the commercial editions of xTuple ERP,
          you can search for Inventory across multiple Sites.</para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the QUERY button</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The following screen shows sample results:</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/Invavail.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Inventory Availability</caption>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>As you can see in our example, we learned there are 30 units of Item
    YTRUCK1 currently available at our Site ST1. If we had chosen to view
    availability at All Sites, we could have gotten an even wider view of Item
    availability.</para>
    <tip>
      <para>You can also can identify Items that are currently on order by
      right-clicking on the Item. In this way, you can find out further
      details regarding estimated delivery of order.</para>
    </tip>
  </section>
</chapter>
